welcome to meditating with john viveki
we live stream every weekday morning at
9 30 a.m with mondays alternating
between
a new lesson called dharma day and a
review of the whole ecology called
pi day i apologize yesterday for the
technical difficulties we had so we
couldn't hold the class but we were able
to resolve them
if you're joining us for the first time
welcome and it might be a little bit
unusual for me standing up and in front
of a white board
for a meditation class but what i
recommend you do is continue meeting
with us but go to
the description for this video and
you'll find links for previous
lessons and sets immediately do lesson
one try to do one or two lessons every
week
and then while you're meeting with us
you'll you'll quite quickly
catch up and integrate with us
i would ask all of you uh to please like
this video stream
uh to increase its visibility in the
youtube algorithm so we can
reach as many people as possible with
this at the end of every session
there is a q a please limit the
questions at that time to the ecology of
practices
however you can ask questions from any
lesson
that has been given if you have more
general questions please come
to the third friday of the month for
live streaming on
youtube at 3 p.m and that'll be august
21st this month
and that's for general q a
so um i think that's everything for now
and
let's move into a little bit of quick
review i did an extensive review
um on wednesday a little bit of kick
review and then extend a little bit more
uh the epicureanism so let's remember
uh some of the things we're doing we're
doing
some kind of self-examination practice
it's a good thing to note
if you can right um
uh the things the commissions things
that you did
that were not virtuous or not
a way of cultivating the wisdom etc
things that you admitted to do is it two
ends for a minute i don't know
mission uh that you admitted to do
and then of course try to note instances
of virtue
uh for some of you who are already doing
it um
there's of course an element it can be
drawn in from stoicism
i do the bias work i try to notice or
remember uh any bias
uh that i uh was trying to track
throughout the day or any of the ones
that i've been learning about
we'll come back to the uh you can add in
which i do too
uh recording your dreams and that's
gonna come in from neoplatonic tradition
theorgia especially sort of a young
approach to that
then we talked about maximization
this is to the record you may draw it
from your alexa divinia you may
draw it from some of the books you're
reading especially the mclaren
right um you may draw it up from
other people these are maxims that you
try to memorize
and recite and so that they're ready to
hand um
they're ready to hand when you are
uh well particularly for epicureanism
when you're engaging in the frame
widening
the maximum should invoke a principle
that commits you to the widest
framing of your experience remember when
we talked about this on wednesday this
is also
the right your identification framing
it's not just
of what you're aware of but how you're
identifying with it
and then we took a look at the epicurean
model which is basically like a medical
model
uh call no man a philosopher who has not
alleviated the suffering of others
that's from epicurus
um and oh i wanted to say one more thing
about this
one thing that the followers of
epicureans did
was they would actually inscribe the
maxims all about their
their dwelling place they would put them
on their hairbrush or
take them on the wall put them on their
cups and that's a very powerful strategy
by the way for
learning your maxims okay so back to
epicurus and alleviating suffering i'm
just going to go over this briefly
because
you did it in detail which you
the idea is what we're seeking and we're
going to what we're going to extend to
today is what this word means
at araxia and the idea is um
we suffer because we lack ataraxia
we're in turmoil and tumult in
conflict and we are that way because we
have we have uneducated desires
or we seek pleasure or avoid pain
which is also fear uh so let's let's do
that again we have uneducated desires
and fears
or we have we're uneducated in our
approach of pleasure
or in our avoidance of pain and that's
what calls causes it's
too much so we want to bring rational
reflection and rational discernment
to bear on the way we experience and
identify with our pleasures
and so the desire
like i said i think this is a bit of a
mistake on epicurus part i don't think
we desire
pleasure i think we desire things that
give us pleasure and
and they give us pleasure precisely
because they are good for us
in some way that's a neoplatonic
criticism but let's leave it like this
for now
uh just for practical purposes uh some i
think i believe it was
kira that has a question about like this
is kind of nebulous and hard
what can i how can i get a hold of this
um
and there's often some resistance around
this so one way of thinking about this
about the notion of desire and right is
so think about
these three things
okay so when you're about to do
something
what's motivating you what's your
motivating uh affect
um so you know there's a want or a need
or an
urge these all fall under what's called
desire
that you look at the motive that's one
aspect of it that you look at
what's the goal okay now these are all
bound together this is a
this is a way of analyzing it so this is
to bring acuity
to your reflection on your desires you
look at the motive
you look at the goal and then you look
at your anticipated sense of reward
what is it you anticipate you'll
experience not well not with not what
not the state of affairs in the world
that's your goal but once you achieve
that goal
you eat the chocolate right um what's
what's your anticipated sense of reward
is it a physical sensation
is it emotional release is it a sense of
security
is it distraction except what's the
sense of reward what's your motive
what's your goal that so if you sort of
open up this triangle
of the aspects that can help you get a
more acute
um and perhaps even more precise
or at least accurate um take on your
desire
so then what we do is we step back and
like in the labeling practice within the
buddhist tradition
we but we do more than label we
categorize catalog
our desires we ask a sequence of
questions because what are we seeking
how are we seeking anorexia
we're trying to prioritize prior
the ties ease
of sustainability
and part of what we're trying to do is
we're instead of confusing
intensity with
importance we're trying to learn to
intensify
what is most rationally reflectively
discerned as
important so we ask
first of all is it a mental or physical
pleasure
and we are to we are to prioritize
remember
prioritize does not mean to exclude it
means to prioritize
we have to prioritize mental pleasures
over physical pleasures
for both mental and physical pleasures
we go through a sequence of questions
is it natural is it needed is it
constitutive
do we is it like import right
do we need to take it in in order to
remain physically
healthy not just merely alive but
healthy
vital so again not just a passive sense
well i survived another day
but that sense of no i have vitality
mental again not just remain
having a mind but you have a mind that
is healthy that is vital
i suggested that the main thing you want
to concentrate when you're looking for
the life of the mind
is you want to look at those things that
give you an enhanced sense of meaning in
life
and what seems to be constitutive of
meaning in life
is connectedness to oneself to others to
the world
and how how much things make sense to us
and then a sense that we have a
direction in which we're moving
your social life we're gonna like i keep
putting that off because i have a lesson
dedicated to that for you
when we zero in on the epicurean um
notion of friendship and friendship is
the central thing
in epicureanism it's the central thing
that encourages us
and helps us deal with both our desires
and our fears
so we ask is it natural
is it neces is it necessary
and then we ask is it short-term
or long-term and this is where the
maximization comes in
and then after we've done that we ask
about ease of sustainability
and then in order to give us a
phenomenological touchstone
of what
we should be seeking when we're seeking
anorexia
give you the practice of trying to turn
the world into a garden as you go for a
walk
and this is new research the idea of
savoring
remember that has two components i'm
opening up my perception of the world
and i'm activating my prehension
of all the relationships and patterns
and so as i'm moving around
i'm paying attention to like textures uh
the tempo
the emotional tone i'm i'm getting
a kind of shamanic synesthesia so when i
come to this i almost feel like i'm
the the board or the floor
and so i'm i'm participating in right a
sense of
presencing and what that gives me is
something like a flow state
and that flow state and we'll come back
to that a little bit that flow state is
puts us in touch with the most important
what i want to say species but it's it's
an exemplar yeah that's what i want
one of the most important exemplars of
anorexia which is the pure
joy of being anorexia doesn't mean just
the freedom from tumult
it means the very powerfully present
positive pleasure of the pure
presence of being
and that's what you use as a touchstone
so
the the maximization and the savoring
act as
sort of a sets of constraints that help
you zero in
help you hone in on how you should
be uh seeking anorexia
all right now that brings me into what i
want to talk about right now
just to
extend it a little bit more for us and
then we get into the set into some
questions
and this is this is not in what i'm
going to teach now is not in
epicurus but it is very much in the
spirit of epicurus because as i
mentioned
epicurus has committed to science he was
a proponent of the atomic theory for
example
and an early proponent of you know
psychological theorizing
and this has to do with two different
ways in which we can think about
anorexia and this has to do with work
from
michael actor he's a psychologist
michael actor talks about
meta-motivational
modes you can tell he's an academic
right
now we know what a mode is we've already
talked about that when we talked about
meta
right it's it's the co-identification
but he talks about here he uses this
term he's talking about the that there's
two ways in which we frame
and identify our arousal now this word
is
often misunderstood because of freud
arousal doesn't just mean sexual arousal
arousal is any sense of intensifying
your metabolic metabolic activation
and energizing yourself you're aroused
right and so you can be very aroused by
a symphony
right etc okay
so after pointed out that
we actually have most people were
thinking
and i think this is a mistake that is in
epicurus most people think of arousal
just
as a more or less of a single state
but actor actually obtained evidence and
made good arguments for the following
things so what i wanna
what this here is my level of arousal
so this this means arousal is increasing
this here is what's called your hedonic
tone
this is how pleasurable how positive
this
is to you and when he noted and what he
provided evidence for and this has
increased
uh since he first proposed it and what
he calls reversal theory
and it lines up with other work that
quite chicks up behind others
is he proposed that there was two
different modes
in which we relate to our arousal why am
i doing all this
because i'm trying to give you a more
sophisticated and nuanced understanding
of how we seek anorexia
okay
in one form
when we have very
high levels of arousal
we experience that as very negative
but when we have very low levels of
arousal
we experience that as very positive
and this is the prevalent model by the
way that people have
the idea is i work very hard and then i
get to a place
that is right where i can relax and then
that's where i actually experience
uh most of the pleasure right so it
looks like this
low levels of arousal very high hedonic
tone
and then it goes down like that he
called this the telec mode
notice the word i used work
so in metallic mode we have an activity
and the activity is for the sake of the
goal
so right i'm doing something in order to
get to the goal state and the goal state
is what i want
so when my activity is very very high
i have i'm very frustrated because high
activity
means i haven't reached the desired goal
state
but when my arousal is low that means
i've either abandoned it and then i'm
usually sort of sad or i've achieved it
in which case i now feel very very happy
okay so this is relaxation contentment
this is frustration
that's italic mode
t loss means a purpose that you're
working towards
now but what do you really when he
pointed out this there's another mode
that's exactly the opposite
now both of these don't both go to
infinity or anything like that so this
is
right well limited within sort of the
the natural range
of human variability so
he calls this the peritolic mode which
is very similar to
uh shakespeare high the guy who did all
the work on flow his
idea of the auto metallic mode
so this is right
more like play this is
we have an activity but we set up goals
but the goals are for the sake of the
activity
so what's what's an obvious example when
i'm playing music i have a goal to get
to the end
but if i could shortcut it and get to
the end faster i don't go hey that's
great let's just hit it i can skip the
song and i can just get to the final
hole
wow that's great i'm at the at the end
you know what no no
the goal is just to give you a structure
for an activity that is inherently
valuable
so now what you're doing is you're doing
the we're doing
the activity for its own sake the
problem we have with the word i just
used is we tend to
think it as only pertaining to trivial
activities
to frivolous and trivial things play is
just
about fun and that's a big mistake
now when i have very low levels of
arousal than peritelic
that's boredom
that's not that's not pleasurable
but when i have high levels this is
excitement
or even as i mentioned
flow
the flow state remember what that is we
talked about it when we talked about
finding your flow
that's the state in which you're
absorbed and although you're expending a
lot of metabolic energy you're in the
zone
and it feels like it's almost it's
paradoxical it feels almost
effortless graceful and it's
it is both optimally hedonic for you
and you're also doing your optimal
performance at whatever task you're
engaged in
so i'm going to now erase this
so if you want to take another quick
look at it right
so we have it's not so crowded visually
crowded for you
okay so the solid line is italic mode
the dotted line is
the peritonic mode and what that means
is we actually have two anoraxias
we have this
and we have this
and i think that although epicurus often
talks about this
this is implicitly what he is seeking
why do i think that what's my argument
for that
because his primary example of the
optimal state which
people can be in is in deep flowing
philosophical
conversation
this
but he often talks this way now the fact
that somebody as
i don't know brilliant as epicurus
i think is confusing these two should
wake us up to the fact that just like we
can be modally confused
about the having and the being modes and
these probably map onto
having mode and v8 mode by the way
we can be modelly confused about how
we're seeking
ataraxia now this anoraxia
is good but it tends to be what
james cars calls a finite game
because finite games are finite because
the point of the game is to get to the
goal
and then be entitled you're the winner
you deserve the relaxation
these are what he calls infinite gains
you play them for their own sake and the
point of the game is to figure out how
to constantly
shift the parameters of the game so that
you can continue to play it
so it's very important when you're
seeking anorexia
to make sure you're not confusing these
and if right and to make sure you're
also clear
that of the two this is the one that
actually has
the more sustainability to it again
i am not saying that this is not
anorexia
it is but again just like we don't want
to
prioritize physical pleasures over
mental pleasures
but we still pursue physical pleasures
we don't want to prioritize
this anorexia over this
anorexia we need to learn
how to play infinite games that put us
into the flow
state that allow us to save your saver
the pure joy of being
at all at all levels of our life our
social life
our mental life and our physical life
okay there isn't a specific
practice but i wanted to
like part of what i'm trying to do on
behalf of epicurus is
educate you but extend it in terms of
more recent science
so we can get a better understanding of
anorexia
how we can be confused about anorexia
and
why philosophical conversation was
actually so
central to epicurus and that's a
practice i'm going to be teaching you
extensively on the next time next uh
dharma day and the following review
sessions
okay so i'm just going to erase the
board i'm going to move the board
i'm going to get my mat and pillow
jason's going to adjust the camera
and then we're going to sit as usual we
will
chant for a bit we'll go into a sit and
then we'll do some questions
all right everyone please prepared get
yourself into your basic posture
set your phones on do not disturb and we
will begin when i say begin
we will start with chanting
begin on
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
on
[Laughter]
one
begin your silence set
uh
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness
cognition character and communicates
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
um
so uh let's begin to address some
questions let's remember
that on monday wednesday and friday we
will give priority to questions from
the western wisdom tradition and
thursday and friday we will give
priority to
uh the eastern wisdom tradition uh a
reminder also to please
share uh observations and questions
uh and comments uh your observations and
your comments are edifying and helpful
uh to other people um so
uh well here's a question from kira uh
i've noticed some resistance
attempts coming up at the thought of it
and applying desires
i also noticed when i tried it's a
little nebulous and something i can't
quite pin down so
on here i try to answer i try to in an
anticipatory
fashion answer the second part of your
question in terms of how to bring acuity
um sensitivity to cutie almost like the
fire factors from mindfulness
uh to your desires uh in terms of
looking for that sort of triangle
of of motive goal and anticipated reward
uh the resistant intention coming up but
the thought of identity desires
you might want to sit uh with that
resistance in in
meditation and bring acquiring
mindfulness
on it and perhaps also direct meta
towards it
uh what's trying to express itself what
what what do you need to listen to
um what's going on there perhaps there's
uh
some some past issues of how people um
have
not properly recognized or evaluated
your desires or perhaps
uh there might be some fear around your
desires because perhaps
certain sets of desires are uh to have
been
sort of very powerful you uh and
therefore
they come tinged with a bit of anxiety
um it could be any of those none of
those
all all of those more beyond those uh
but i'm just giving those as an example
of the kind of thing
you can bring into reflection about that
lin lin slater welcome lin always
good to have you here um observation
thinking about mental desires
most of my my unhelpful thought patterns
or mental addictions self-soothing
strategies that occasionally work
causing pernicious partial reinforcement
yeah um so
that the and the the idea of addiction
is right there's a reciprocal narrowing
um in our relationship
to the world and to our desires um
and that shrinks the framing down
and we more and more get focused on
addressing the intensity
uh rather than the importance of the
effective state this
this happens to me
quite frequently and so um
you know the strategies of maximization
of frame whitening
of trying to remind yourself
um that there are more long-term
sustainable um mental pleasures
a part of it also though um is uh
to give a place where uh
people can address fear
um we've only talked somewhat also
mostly about the desire side of this
um and the trick there
is to find a place between just
discussing a topic
and just doing therapy but to get it
into something that is not just first
person therapeutic
perspective or the third person
theoretical perspective
it's to get into sort of a second person
perspective
um which would talk a lot more when we
do
uh the philosophical companionship
that's how her talks about it
and that's a place that can help us get
out of some of these self-reinforcing
patterns
so that's all we have time for for today
we're already going longer i have
forewarned you guys that
uh monday wednesdays and fridays will
tend to be longer
because this has a little bit more of a
socratic
aspect to it which is completely
appropriate because since socrates is
the exemplary figure
we will of course keep track of all
questions that have not yet been
answered
and we will address them uh on the ones
we will continue to address them next
week especially with the ones from
wisdom hypatia
on monday i want to thank you all for
joining i want to thank my dear friend
and technical maj amar
my beloved son jason for helping to set
things up and moving the cameras around
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified about the next video
you'll also find links to the lecture
series awakening from the meeting crisis
the dialogue series where i'm trying to
exemplify the dialectic that's at the
core of neoplatonism
um you'll find voices with verbacy there
there is a series coming out soon on uh
the unconsciousness called untangling
the world not the hard problem
of meaning and mine and then
there is a series that's going to be
coming up probably beginning of next
year
on the nature of the south and then the
the big series that i'm working on
will be analogous to waking from the
meetings our crisis is
um after socrates and you're beginning
we are already after socrates in the
wisdom of hypatia
and that you're getting a sense of what
that course will be about
please follow me on twitter for updates
on the uh
about these streams if it's not against
your principles please invite others who
might benefit by sharing these series
please join the discord server to chat
with others do the group
lectio under the group movement
practices and also
you will find a home there for some of
the group practices that we're going to
need
uh from for the wisdom of my patient
monday we're doing this every weekday
morning at 9 30 eastern time
and i think that's everything
so please remember that continuity of
practice is more important than sheer
quantity
don't hold yourself to the standard of a
harsh perfectionism
but to the standard of a virtuous
friendship because
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind and body there is no ally no
true companion no friend at the curious
friendship
right greater than your own mind and
body
elapse unto yourselves and to each other
i'll see you all on monday take good
care have a good weekend
you